Finding Aid for Katherine Moore Cushman Papers 1950-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Katherine Moore Cushman Papers 1950-1970
Cushman, Katherine Moore.
4 linear feet
Local and state League of Women Voters official, Dearborn, Michigan, civic activist. Papers relating to her organizational involvements, especially Church Women United, 1962-1969; the Citizens Committee for Equal Opportunity, 1963-1969; the Governor's Special Conservation Study Committee, 1963-1964; the state office and Dearborn chapter of the League of Women Voters, 1950-1970; the Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1963; the Michigan Council of Churches, 1963-1969; the Northwestern Child Guidance Clinic, 1962-1966; also files relating to her opposition to parochiaid, or public funding of private schools; and photograph.
85135 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Cushman (donor no. 4725 ) and came to the library in May 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Katherine Moore Cushman, an active member of many civic, school, and church organizations, is a lifelong resident of Dearborn. She is a graduate of the Dearborn Public Schools and received an A.B. degree in psychology from The University of Michigan in 1938.
One of her major interests has been the League of Women Voters. She served two terms as president of the Detroit League, is a founder and former board member of the Dearborn League, and is a past president of the Michigan League. She was the chief author of Dearborn and Its Government and a contributing author of several other League publications.
An active proponent for a state constitutional convention, in the early 1960s, Mrs. Cushman gave talks, wrote letters, and organized poll workers. She was elected a delegate to the convention and served on the Local Government, and Style and Drafting Committees. After the convention delegates had completed their work, Cushman became a vigorous campaigner for adoption of the proposed new constitution.
Mrs. Cushman also took an active part in the effort to stop parochiaid. She was a member of Citizens to Advance Public Education, and through this and other organizations, was involved in writing and speaking engagements.
A member of Christ Episcopal Church, Mrs. Cushman has been involved in the work of her congregation and in ecumenical organizations. She was the first woman elected to the vestry of her church, and has held office, been a board member, and newsletter editor for Church Women United in Michigan and the Michigan Council of Churches.
Mrs. Cushman is married to Edward L. Cushman, former Vice-President of American Motors Corporation and Executive Vice-President of Wayne State University. He has also been actively involved in groups such as the Coordinating Committee for Constitutional Convention, Citizens to Advance Public Education, Citizens Committee for Equal Opportunity, and the Michigan Council of Churches. The Cushmans have two children, Bob and Betsy.
The papers, 1950-1970, of Katherine Moore Cushman reflect her involvement in several organizations. They have been arranged alphabetically by organization.
Subjects:
Church schools--Michigan--Finance.; Church Women United in Michigan.; Citizens Committee for Equal Opportunity.; Civic leaders--Michigan--Dearborn.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Cushman, Katherine Moore.; Dearborn (Mich.); Government aid to private schools--Michigan.; League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.; League of Women Voters of Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan Council of Churches.; Michigan. Governor's Special Conservation Study Committee.; Northwestern Child Guidance Clinic.; Parochiaid.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Dearborn.; Women--Michigan--Dearborn--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Cushman, Katherine Moore.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Church Women United in Michigan
  Church Women United files (1962-1969) contain correspondence and other papers relating to her work as legislative chairman, issues of the Michigan Church Woman with articles written by Mrs. Cushman, and speech notes. Issues discussed in the articles and speeches are civil rights, gambling, and tax reform.
  - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1962-1969 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Chairman 1963-1966 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Church Woman 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions of Annual Assembly 1966 (Box 1)
  - Talks by Mrs. Cushman (Box 1)
- Citizens Committee for Equal Opportunity
  Minutes, correspondence, financial statements, press releases, and membership lists are included in the full committee files of Citizens Committee for Equal Opportunity (1963-1969). Subcommittee files contain memoranda, brief meeting notes, and reports, with the exception of public accommodations, which consists of a report only.
  - Full Committee 1963-1969, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Subcommittees
    - Housing 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Police-Community Relations 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Public Accommodations 1965 (Box 1)
- Governor's Special Conservation Study Committee
  Mrs. Cushman was appointed by Governor Romney to the Governor's Special Conservation Study Committee. These files (1963-1964) contain correspondence, reports prepared for and by the committee, and papers relating to the work of the Parks and Outdoor Recreation Subcommittee. As a member of this subcommittee, Mrs. Cushman did a study of the park needs of southeastern Michigan.
  - Correspondence 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Parks and Outdoor Recreation Subcommittee 1963 (Box 1)
  - Reports 1963
    - Subcommittees (Box 1)
    - Wildlife Management Institute (Box 1)
- League of Women Voters
  League of Women Voters files (1950-1970) contain papers relating to Mrs. Cushman's work with the Detroit and Dearborn-Dearborn Heights Leagues. These papers consist of personal correspondence relating to league matters, notes and writings relating to various committees and issues, and Mrs. Cushman's file as general chairman of the 1965 state convention For her work at the state level and as president of the state league, the researcher should consult the papers of the League of Women Voters of Michigan. Additional material relating to her work at the local level can be found in the papers of the League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights.
  - Committees/Issues
    - Apportionment 1965 (Box 1)
    - Children's Services 1950-1956 (Box 1)
    - Courts 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - Parochiaid 1969 (Box 1)
    - Taxation-Education 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1950-1965 (Box 1)
  - Know Your Wayne County (League publication)
    - Pre-Publication Manuscript (Box 1)
    - Survey Committee 1952-1961 (Box 1)
  - State Convention 1965 (Box 1)
- Michigan Constitutional Convention
  Papers relating to the Michigan Constitutional Convention (1961-1963) have been arranged into pre-convention, convention, and post-convention series. Pre-convention papers relate to Mrs. Cushman's campaign to be a convention delegate and consist of correspondence, clippings, campaign literature, and financial statements. Convention files consist of articles and newsletters written by Mrs. Cushman, correspondence, proposals, and testimony and statements of individuals and groups. There are action journals for the Local Government and Style and Drafting Committees, and topical files on the issues and levels of local government., Post-convention files relate to the campaign for adoption of the new constitution, and consist of correspondence, writings, speech notes, and pro and con campaign materials. Included in the pro materials is a series of twenty-five articles written by Mrs. Cushman and several members of the League of Women Voters. The Coordinating Committee for the New Constitution was a major force in the campaign, and their files contain bylaws, minutes, and papers relating to the election recount. Mrs. Cushman was Wayne County recount chairman.
  - Campaign 1961
    - Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Congratulatory Letters (Box 1)
    - Democratic Party (Box 1)
    - Elections
      - General (Box 1)
      - Primary (Box 1)
    - Financial Statements (Box 1)
  - Convention 1961-1962
    - Articles and Newsletter written by Mrs. Cushman (Box 1)
    - Church-State Issues (re public funds for private schools) (Box 1)
    - Civil Rights
      - Individual Rights (Box 2)
      - Sex Discrimination (Box 2)
    - Committee Assignments
      - Local Government
        - Action Journal
          - October-December 1961 (Box 2)
          - January-April 1962 (Box 2)
        - Annexation and Incorporation (Box 2)
        - Cities and Villages (Box 2)
        - County Home Rule, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Data on Local Governments (Box 2)
        - Metropolitan Government (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Natural Resources (Box 2)
        - Notes taken by Mrs. Cushman (Box 2)
        - Proposals, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Public Health (Box 2)
        - Public Utilities (Box 2)
        - Style and Drafting Changes for Second Reading (Box 2)
        - Townships
          - General File (Box 2)
          - Tax Rates (1959) (Box 2)
        - Style and Drafting (Action Journal and Memoranda) (Box 2)
    - Committee for a Sound Constitution (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Constituent 1961-1962, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Family October 1961-April 1962 (Box 2)
    - Democratic Party, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Executive Branch (Box 3)
    - Finance and Taxation (Box 3)
    - Internal Improvements (Box 3)
    - Legislative Apportionment
      - Congressional Redistricting (Box 3)
      - Maps and Population Figures (Box 3)
      - Minutes and Action Journal (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Plans Submitted (Box 3)
      - Readings
        - First (Box 3)
        - Second (Box 3)
    - Legislature (Box 3)
    - Lotteries, Sweepstakes, etc. (Box 3)
    - Notes on Convention (Box 3)
    - Preface to Address to the People (Box 3)
    - Proposals submitted by Mrs. Cushman (Box 3)
  - Post-Convention (Campaign for new Constitution) 1962-1963
    - Appearances by Mrs. Cushman (Speech Notes and Correspondence), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign Materials
      - Anti new constitution (Box 3)
      - Pro new constitution
        - Articles written by members of League of Women Voters (Box 3)
        - Other pro materials (Box 3)
    - Citizens Research Council (Box 3)
    - Con-Con Weekly Report (Box 3)
    - Coordinating Committee for the New Constitution
      - Bylaws, Minutes (Box 3)
      - Dearborn and Detroit Chapters (Box 3)
      - Recount
        - Organization of Recount (Box 3)
        - Results (Box 3)
        - Rules and Procedures (Box 3)
    - Correspondence April 1962-July 1963, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Election Returns (Box 4)
    - Lawyers for the new constitution (Box 4)
    - Michigan Congress of Parents and Teachers (Box 4)
    - Provisions of new Constitution
      - Apportionment (Box 4)
      - Civil Rights (Box 4)
      - Civil Service (Box 4)
      - School Finance (Box 4)
    - Response to Citizens Committee to Defend Michigan's Constitution (Box 4)
- Michigan Council of Churches
  Michigan Council of Churches papers (1963-1969) consist of correspondence, public issue files, and papers relating to Mrs. Cushman's work as chairman of the Legislative Affairs Committee and editor of the Lansing Legislative Memo. These files closely parallel the issues and committee work of Church Women United.
  - Correspondence 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - Lansing Legislative Memo 1964-1966, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Affairs Committee 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - Legislative seminars 1965-1969 (Box 4)
  - Public Issues
    - Children and Youth 1966 (Box 4)
    - Gambling 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Housing 1968 (Box 4)
    - Migrant Labor 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Tax Reform 1963-1965 (Box 4)
- Northwestern Child Guidance Clinic
  Mrs. Cushman was a member of the Board of Directors of the Northwestern Child Guidance Clinic from 1912 to 1966, and chairman of the Personnel Policies Committee in 1965. These files consist of bylaws, minutes, statistical clinic reports, budgets, correspondence and memoranda, and historical background of the clinic.
  - Board Minutes and Clinic Reports 1962-1966, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Budgets 1963-1967 (Box 4)
  - Bylaws (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda 1962, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Historical Background of the Clinic (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Personnel Policies Committee 1965-1966 (Box 4)
- Parochiaid
  Mrs. Cushman worked with several groups that were opposed to public funding for private schools. Parochiaid files (1966-1970) consist of papers relating to the activities of these organizations and Mrs. Cushman's speech notes and writings.
  - CAPE (Citizens to Advance Public Education)
    - Dearborn Chapter 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Michigan
      - 1966 (Box 4)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Council of Churches; Church Women United 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Proposal C 1970 (Box 4)
  - Speeches and Writings of Mrs. Cushman (Box 4)
  - STOPS (Spend Taxes on Public Schools) 1968 (Box 4)
- Other Organizations and Miscellaneous
  Other Organizations and Miscellaneous consists of two folders relating to the Wayne County Charter Commission (1968) and Wayne County Citizens Advisory Committee on Community Improvement (1962-1964). Mrs. Cushman was a candidate for the charter commission, and this file contains clippings, press releases, and campaign statements. The community improvement file consists of the statement of purpose of the committee, correspondence and memoranda, and scattered minutes. Also in this series is a photographic portrait of Mrs. Cushman.
  - Wayne County Charter Commission (Cushman Candidacy) 1968 (Box 4)
  - Wayne County Citizens Advisory Committee on Community Improvement 1962-1964 (Box 4)
  - Photograph portrait (Box 4)